Barbara Sapinsley Papers
Oskar Diethelm Library
Barbara Sapinsley Papers
1954 - 1994
This collection contains Barbara Sapinsley papers for her book on Elizabeth Ware Packard published in 1991, The Private War of Mrs. Packard: The Dramatic Story of a Nineteenth-Century Feminist. The collection has 3 series: Research Files, Book Manuscript and Publication, and Correspondence.
5 boxes (2.09 linear feet)
Sapinsley, Barbara
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1991.0001
Gift of Barbara Sapinsley, 1991.
The materials have been kept in the original order and provided with labels by the creator.
This collection is open for research.
Barbara Sapinsley’s book The Private War of Mrs. Packard: The Dramatic Story of a Nineteenth-Century Feminist was published in 1991 by Paragon House. It includes a foreword by Dr. Eric T. Carlson, the former director of the DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry. The subject of the book is Elizabeth Ware Packard, and the cover of the book describes it as “the dramatic story of the 19th century feminist who lobbied for laws to protect wives from husbands who could commit them to mental institutions without legitimate cause.”
Sapinsley, Barbara; Packard, E. P. W. (Elizabeth Parsons Ware), 1816-1897; Packard, S. W. (Samuel Ware), 1847-1937; Packard, Theophilus, 1802-1885; Oglesby, Richard J. (Richard James), 1824-1899; McFarland, Andrew, 1817-1891; Himelhoch, Myra Samuels (1917-1977); Carlson, Eric T., 1922-; Jacksonville Insane Asylum (Ill.); Anti-Insane Asylum Society; Antipsychiatry; Women social reformers -- United States
This collection contains Barbara Sapinsley papers for her book on Elizabeth Ware Packard published in 1991, The Private War of Mrs. Packard: The Dramatic Story of a Nineteenth-Century Feminist. There are three series in this collection.
Research Files: this series contains records on Elizabeth Ware Packard collected over many decades that were used to write the book, including transcriptions and photocopies of original materials.
Book Manuscript and Publication: book drafts and documents on the publication of the book can be found in this series.
Correspondence: this has letters relating to the book, including fan mail and the book’s repeated rejection for publication.
- Research Files
  - Miscellaneous materials used for book, 1964; 1968; 1978; 1981; 1987; Undated (Box 1)
  - Trial, 1970 - 1971; Undated (Box 1)
  - Packard family data, 1958; 1963; 1965 - 1966; 1972; 1978; 1981; 1990 - 1991; Undated (Box 1)
  - Theophilus Packard diary transcription, Undated (Box 1)
  - Theophilus Packard letters, Undated (Box 1)
  - Insanity, general, 1965 - 1968; 1972 - 1975; 1979; 1986; Undated (Box 1)
  - Illinois State Hospital for the Insane 1868 special report of the trustees, Undated (Box 1)
  - Richard James Oglesby letters on Jacksonville, Undated (Box 1)
  - Jonathan Turner materials, character witness for Dr. Andrew McFarland, Undated (Box 1)
  - Anti-religious and preachers [articles from The New York Review], 1989 (Box 1)
  - Library references, 1964; 1970 - 1971; Undated (Box 1)
  - Legislative report and Dr. Andrew McFarland’s response, Undated (Box 2)
  - Medical doctors on Elizabeth Packard, 1968; 1971; 1985; Undated (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts lobbying and family visit, 1981; Undated (Box 2)
  - Old letters on Elizabeth Packard and obituaries, 1965; 1978; Undated (Box 2)
  - Laws circa 1871 and 1880s on insanity, Undated (Box 2)
  - Dr. Andrew McFarland biography, Undated (Box 2)
  - Ware family data, 1965 - 1966; 1977; 1987; 1991; Undated (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Packard’s commitment papers and Worcester, 1977 - 1978; 1987; 1989; Undated (Box 2)
  - Revision research, 1990; Undated (Box 2)
  - Notes from Elizabeth Ware Packard books and secondary sources, Undated (Box 2)
  - Religion in general notes and newspaper clippings, 1965 - 1967; 1975; 1990 - 1991; Undated (Box 2)
  - Book notebooks, Undated (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Ware Packard lobbying notes and correspondence, 1966; 1973; 1981; Undated (Box 3)
  - Springfield and Jacksonville newspapers on Illinois investigation, Undated (Box 3)
  - Reproductions of photographs, 1989 - 1990; Undated (Box 3)
- Book Manuscript and Publication
  - Early outlines including fictionalized treatment, Undated (Box 3)
  - Draft for Eric T. Carlson preface, Undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Proposal on Elizabeth Ware Packard, Undated (Box 4)
  - Paragon House correspondence, researchers, and photo reproductions, 1966; 1972; 1975; 1977; 1989 - 1991; Undated (Box 4)
  - Reviews, 1991 - 1992; Undated (Box 4)
  - Manuscript corrected, c. 1991 (Box 4)
  - Layout copy from publisher, c. 1991; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Master pages from publisher, 1991 (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  - “There is life after rejections” article and correspondence, 1992 - 1993 (Box 5)
  - Twenty years of rejection correspondence photocopies, Undated (Box 5)
  - Myra Himelhoch article and correspondence, 1974 - 1976; 1987; Undated (Box 5)
  - Agents and editors, 1966 - 1968; 1975; 1977 - 1985; 1987 - 1989; Undated (Box 5)
  - Twentieth century Packards, 1954; 1961; 1965 - 1969; 1971 - 1973; 1976; 1981; 1987; Undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1959; 1961; 1964 - 1966; 1968 - 1973; 1975; 1977 - 1978; 1986 - 1987; 1989; 1991 - 1992; Undated (Box 5)
  - Fan mail, 1984; 1991 - 1992; 1994; Undated (Box 5)
  - John F. Graham “The Brain Butchers” manuscript, 1973 (Box 5)